Mattermost is a secure
collaboration hub trusted by
cyber defense and critical
infrastructure organizations.
It offers on premise and
private cloud deployment for
strict data control.
Unlike other cloud based
collaboration tools,
which may go down
during a cyber attack,
Mattermost can run out of band,
ensuring defenders stay
operational and isolated from
compromised infrastructure.
It integrates with the Microsoft
stack including Azure and EntraID,
as well as upcoming
integrations with critical
security tools like Sentinel,
Defender, and Intune.
Whether you're replacing
siloed chat apps,
inefficient email chains,
or other legacy tools,
Mattermost is the command
center for secure operations.
From mitigating cybersecurity
incidents to streamlining
operational coordination,
Mattermost increases the
effectiveness of mission
critical workflows.
In this example scenario,
a security operations center
uses Mattermost to accelerate
incident response out of band.
They use a shared channel with
their managed security services
provider for monitoring alerts.
By securely connecting
two Mattermost instances,
both organizations can
collaborate in real time.
A new alert from the SIM system
posts to the monitoring channel.
The team lead sends an urgent
message notifying impacted
personnel who then acknowledge
they've read the message.
A Mattermost Playbook is
then initiated to execute incident
response procedures.
The playbook creates a
dedicated channel with a
standardized checklist, auto invites
key stakeholders, and guides each
step of the incident response.
Throughout the incident,
team members mark task progress,
post status updates, and share
intel in real time.
Playbooks can be templated and
customized to fit any workflow.
Slash Commands and Webhooks
trigger actions such as initiating
a multi party briefing call
directly from the operational channel.
This pulls the team into a
real time collaboration space.
Live transcription ensures
team members remain informed.
After the call concludes,
chat logs, call transcripts,
and audio recordings are
preserved in the call thread,
providing critical mission documentation
for an after action review.
Mattermost Copilot,
your AI assistant,
extracts key takeaways with
automated call summaries,
delivering concise insights
when every moment counts.
Users can refine summaries with
their preferred model and share
them in the call thread.
With full control over AI
model selection, data access,
and user permissions,
Mattermost ensures access to
AI support in compliance with
security standards.
From coordinating remediation
to tracking incident response
status, Mattermost Boards
provides end to end visibility.
Staff can drag and drop
task cards between columns,
update statuses,
and configure views,
whether in a Kanban
board or table view,
to accommodate the workflow.
With the threat contained,
the playbook run is closed.
Built in reporting provides a timeline
and analysis for retrospective
Mattermost aligns with
modern Zero Trust strategies.
It enforces strict controls
with granular permissions and
supports SAML, LDAP,
and multi factor authentication
for identity and access management.
Segmentation is achieved with
teams and private channels.
And data is protected with TLS
encryption and the ability to
enforce data retention
policies tailored for SecOps.
Mattermost is the future of
cyber defense collaboration.
Connect with us to explore how
Mattermost can transform your
security workflows today.